本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流
更多中日双语字幕，尽在www.kamigami.org 及微博@诸神字幕组
Yes!
そうだ　パルスに災厄を招くのだ
Bring calamity upon Pars!
Daryun.
ダリューン
Lord Uncle.
伯父上
I will protect His Majesty, the King,
国王陛下は　わしがお守りするゆえ
so you go in search of Prince Arslan.
お主は　アルスラーン殿下をお捜ししろ
His Highness?
殿下を
He has not been seen.
お姿が見えぬ　突撃の先頭におられたようだ
It seems he was at the front of the charge.
l am sure he wished to
distinguish himself in battle
武勲を挙げ　王に認めていただきたかったのであろうが…
to be deemed worthy in the King's eyes, but...
I feel uneasy.
心もとないことじゃ
It may be too late, but protect His Highness.
遅まきかもしれぬが　守ってさしあげよ
I will answer to the King's wrath.
王のお怒りは　わしが引き受ける
I understand.
分かりました
伯父上　エクバターナで再会しましょう
Lord Uncle, let us meet again in Ecbatana!
Pars Era, the year 320, autumn.
パルス暦３２０年　秋
圧倒的に有利と思われた　アトロパテネにおける大戦は
The great battle upon Atropatene
was thought to be overwhelmingly in their favor,
but the stratagems employed by the Lusitanians
ルシタニアの策略により　累々たるパルス軍の屍を積み重ねた
heaped the battlefield with piles
upon piles of dead Parsian soldiers.
Prince Arslan's maiden battle was
to have been marked with magnificence,
華々しく飾られるはずであったアルスラーン王子の初陣は
but it became a veritable hell on earth.
さながら　地獄となった
Your Highness!
殿下
Daryun!
ダリューン
l am coming to save you, Your Highness!
今お助けいたします　殿下
These aren't my words
日听&翻译
小伍
sora
兰樱
校对
小江
mam
If the whole world only had left hands
Don't be the bastards who hide their right hands
片源
Rei
时间轴
电池雪糕
压制
久嘉
Coolkid
There's nothing beyond this azure
The day I realized that,
I stopped looking up at the sky
And in the bottomless swamp,
look, there's a bottom
In this town that's growing
even more tainted even now
Even if you just tried to breathe the air
You'd end up breathing in the bad stuff, too
And in the bottomless swamp,
look, there's a bottom
In this town that's growing
even more tainted even now
Even if you just tried to breathe the air
You are friend, Baby Dream
Before I knew it, my heart
Was full of things I had to love all the way
Always losing, leaving
Even the unbearable stuff
Because I don't want to live my days
lamenting, unable to keep them safe
You are friend, Baby, Dream
I'll grow even stronger
These aren't my words
But our words
Daryun.
ダリューン
Your Highness!
殿下
What is the meaning of this, Lord Kharlan?
これはどういうことか　カーラーン殿
Did you betray us, Kharlan?
裏切ったのか　カーラーン
The Knight in Black...
黒衣の騎士
「マルダーン・フ・マルダーン」　ダリューンか
Mardān fu Mardān, Daryun...
Kharlan, why has a man
of your caliber turned traitor?
カーラーン　貴様ほどの男が　なぜ裏切った
This is not treachery.
裏切りではない
It is out of true concern for
the interests of the Kingdom of Pars
まこと　パルス王国のためを思えばこそ
that I aided this plot to dethrone Andragoras.
アンドラゴラスを王位から追う企てに加担したのだ
父上を？　なぜ
My lord father?! Why?!
I see, I understand now.
そうか　分かったぞ
Before the battle, the one who urged
me to advise His Majesty to retreat...
戦いを前にして後退するように陛下に申し上げろと俺に勧めたのは
...was you.
貴様だ
And I would incur His Majesty's displeasure
俺は　陛下のご不興を被って　マルズバーンの任を解かれる
and be dismissed from my post as Marzbān.
That was what you hoped to achieve!
それを　ねらってのことだな
そのとおりだ　ダリューン
It is just as you say, Daryun.
You are strong, but not a fool.
お主は強いが　阿呆ではないな
That is precisely why I...
だからこそ　お主に…
That is precisely why
だからこそ　お主に１万もの騎兵を指揮させるわけにはいかんのだよ
I cannot have you commanding
ten thousand cavalrymen!
No matter how valiant you are,
お主がいかに勇猛でも　単騎で戦況を左右できるものではないからな
even you cannot alter the course
of battle as a lone horseman!
Your Highness, please wait there for a time.
殿下　しばし　そこでお待ちください
For I, Daryun, will keep you safe.
このダリューンがお守りいたしますゆえ
I will leave the rest to you, Daryun.
あとは任せた　ダリューン
Hold, Daryun! Listen to me!
待て　ダリューン　話を聞け
What do you think to say now?!
今更　何を言う
国王陛下を裏切り　王太子殿下にこのようなまねを
After you betrayed His Majesty, the King,
and treated His Highness,
the Crown Prince, in this manner...
Wait! If you learn of the circumstances,
even you would not fault my actions...
待て　事情を知れば　お主とて　俺の行為を責めは…
ここは　一旦　退くぞ
We retreat for now!
カーラーン
Kharlan!
Your Highness!
殿下
You are injured?
おケガを
Oh, no. The blood is not mine.
いや　返り血だ
Kharlan...
カーラーン…　なぜだ　カーラーン…
Why? Kharlan...
Your Majesty,
陛下
we have received word that
Marzbāns Manūchurh and Khayr were killed.
マルズバーン・マヌーチュルフとハイルが討たれたとの伝令が入りました
And as for what has become of the rest...
他の者も　どうなったか…
もはや　この戦いに勝ちはございませぬ
There is no longer a victory
to be had from this battle.
"Eighteenth Monarch, Kingdom of Pars
Andragoras III"
Please withdraw.
お退きくだされ
Retreat.
退却を
Vahriz, you wretch...
ヴァフリーズ　貴様…
予が　武人としての恥を知らぬと思うてか
Do you think I know not the shame of a warrior?!
Your Majesty, please bear the
shame of today in order to win tomorrow!
陛下　明日勝つために　今日の恥をお忍びくだされ
The peace and security
of the Continental Highway
大陸公路の安寧はパルス王の下　不敗の強兵あってこそではないか
depends upon the mighty undefeated army
commanded by the King of Pars!
陛下
Your Majesty!
The Lady Queen is in the Royal Capital.
王妃様のおられる王都を　敵の手に委ねてもよろしいとおっしゃいますか
Would you have it fall
into the hands of the enemy?
We retreat.
退却だ
Yes, sir! Relay the message to every unit!
はっ　各隊に伝えろ
We're retreating!
退却だ
Messengers! Quick!
伝令　急げ
But in this fog...
しかし　この霧では…
Use the horns!
角笛を使え
Message!
伝令だ
Sir!
はっ…
Did you get him?
やったか
Yes, just as Lord Kharlan planned.
ああ　カーラーン様の計画どおりだ
よし　大声でやるぞ
All right. Here we go. Make it loud!
王が逃げた
The King ran away!
The King has run away!
国王が逃げたぞ
He ran! He ran away!
逃げた　逃げたぞ
--It was Lusitania's plot.
--He ran!
ルシタニアの企てであった
King Andragoras has run away!
--At the instigation of men under Kharlan,
--The King ran away!
カーラーン配下の者たちの扇動によって　退却命令は歪曲
--the order to retreat was distorted.
--The King has run away! The King has run away!
--Amidst the confusion and bloodshed,
--The King has run away!
混乱と流血のなか　国王逃亡の流言のみが　戦場を駆け抜けたのである
only the wild rumor of the King's
flight raced across the battlefield.
The King has run away?
国王が逃げた
Abandoning his men?
兵を捨てて
O-Our King Andragoras?
あ…あのアンドラゴラス王が
The Invincible King has ran away?
不敗の王が逃げた
ルシタニアの勝ちだ
Lusitania is victorious!
なんだと
What?
This is absurd!
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Shapur"
バカな
We are here, risking our lives in battle,
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Shapur"
我らが命懸けで戦っておるのに
and the King leading our army runs away?!
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Shapur"
我が軍を統率したもう国王が　お逃げになるとは
パルスの軍旗は泥にまみれた　取り返しがつかぬ
The standard of Pars has
been dragged through the mud.
There is no coming back from this.
やめた　やめた
I quit! I quit!
Who would we be fighting for now?
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Kubard"
もはや　誰のために戦うというのだ
I've no life to offer the likes of a
king who abandons his men and runs.
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Kubard"
部下を捨てて逃げるような君主にささげる命はないわ
We'll be fleeing as we please as well, Shapur.
俺たちも好きなように逃げさせてもらうぞ　シャプール
Kubard! What are you saying?!
クバード　お主　何を言う
You are a Marzbān! And you would
incite your men to quit fighting?!
マルズバーンたるお主が　兵に戦いをやめるよう唆すとは
The King has his
responsibilities and we have ours!
王は王　我らには我らの責務というものが…
Protecting the kingdom is first
and foremost the duty of the king.
国を守るべきは　まず　王の義務
It's that duty that gives a
king the authority of a king.
それあればこそ　王は王としての権威を持つ
The King is no longer worthy of being king.
もはや　王は王たりえず　我らとて同じことだ
And the same applies to us.
You yourself threw down
your helm in rage just now.
お主とて　今　冑をなげうって怒ったではないか
No, that was thoughtlessly done.
いや…　あれは軽はずみであった
The King did not run away!
王はお逃げあそばしたのではない
He must mean to return to
the Royal Capital of Ecbatana
王都エクバターナにお戻りになって　再戦を期されるおつもりであろう
in anticipation of fighting once more!
Huh.
You are a subject of the crown.
If you dishonor His Majesty any further,
お主　臣下の身で　これ以上　陛下を辱めるとあらば
friend or not, I will show you no mercy!
味方とて　容赦はせぬぞ
Oh-ho. Interesting.
面白い
Just how do you intend to show me no mercy?
どう容赦せぬというのだ
We're under attack!
敵襲
Uh-oh.
逃げる気か　クバード
You would run from me, Kubard?!
If we do not drive away that enemy force,
あの敵軍を打ち払わぬことには　退路も作れぬだろうが
there will be no retreat to be had.
After we have taken care of them,
ヤツらを始末してから
let us speak at our leisure upon
the makings of a subject of the crown.
臣下たる者の資質について　ゆっくり語ろうではないか
Eh, Shapur?
なあ　シャプール
You had better not tell me at a
later date that you have forgotten!
後日になって　忘れたなどと言うなよ
I will not forget.
忘れはせんさ　後日というものがあればな
If this later date should come to pass, that is.
On the same day, as dusk fell,
同日　夕刻を前にして
the proudly undefeated
Parsian army led by Andragoras lll
無敗を誇ったアンドラゴラス三世　率いるパルス軍は　大敗を喫した
suffered a crushing defeat.
Those damn savages!
蛮族どもめが
I never imagined that Prince Arslan's
maiden battle would come to this...
よもや　アルスラーン殿下の初陣がこのようなことになろうとは
Daryun, keep His Highness safe.
ダリューン　殿下をお守りいたせ
We should be too far for them to pursue us now.
ここまで来れば　追ってこられまい
Ambush!
伏兵
陛下…
Your Majesty!
Secure the middle!
中央を固めろ
Your Majesty!
陛下
Kharlan, that scoundrel...
カーラーンめが　うまくやってくれたわ
Fine job he did back there.
So, Andragoras, you shamelessly
abandoned your men and fled.
恥知らずにも　部下を見捨てて逃げおったか　アンドラゴラス
It sounds like something you would do.
貴様のやりそうなことよな
You were lying in wait for us?
待ち伏せしていたのか
Yes.
そうだ
The path you were most likely to take
to retreat has long been known to me.
貴様らが選びそうな退路など　すでに承知のうえだ
They are most thinly defended to the fore.
手薄なのは前方
I do not know how skilled he is, but...
あやつが　どれほどの使い手なのか分からぬが…
My King, please run.
王よ　お逃げくだされ　ここは　この老骨が道を開きます
This old man will clear a path.
Men, guard the King!
皆の者　王をお守りしろ
Lord Vahriz!
ヴァフリーズ殿
Go!
行け
Vanquished old fool, do not interfere
where it is not your place to do so!
敗残の老いぼれが　出過ぎたまねをするな
そやつを　王などと呼ぶな
Do not call him a king.
Who the hell are you?
お前は何者だ
You are the object of such hatred
これほどの憎しみを受けながら　私が誰かも分からぬほど
and yet, you do not even know who I am.
悪行を重ねてきたか
Such are the numerous acts
of villainy you have committed!
Sixteen years...
１６年…
I have waited sixteen long years
for this day to come, Andragoras!
この日が来るのを　１６年間待ち続けたぞ
アンドラゴラス
殿下
Your Highness.
Your Highness, the saddle
is soiled with spattered blood,
殿下　返り血まみれの汚れた鞍でございますが
but please get on.
どうぞ　お乗りください
Daryun, this is your horse.
ダリューン　これはお主の馬だ　戦士の馬だ
The horse of a warrior.
I have no business riding him.
私が乗るわけにはいかない
I can fight perfectly well even
on one of these other horses here.
私はそれ　そこらの馬でも　十分戦えます
Please take him as your mount.
どうぞ　こやつにお乗りください
私に万が一がありましたら
In the unlikely event that
something should happen to me,
please touch the whip to Shabrang
シャブラングにひと鞭打って　一気に戦場を駆け抜けてください
and race across the
battlefield without stopping.
こやつの足には　どんな馬も追いつけませぬ
No horse can catch his fleet foot.
お主に　万が一があるのか
Do unlikely events even exist for you?
ありませぬ
No, they do not.
殿下をお守りするため　億が一もありえませぬな
In guarding Your Highness,
not even the remotely unlikely
event will have a chance of happening.
Your Highness, please stay close behind me.
殿下　私の後ろを離れないでください
I am all right. Shabrang understands.
大丈夫だ　シャブラングが理解してくれている
おい　大丈夫か　しっかりしろ
Hey, are you all right? Stay strong.
お主は　確か　シャプール殿の下にいた…
If I remember right,
you served under Lord Shapur...
Lord Shapur has... Lord Shapur has...
シャプール殿が…　シャプール殿…
Calm down. How goes the battle?
落ち着け　戦況は
Of the Marzbān, Lord Manūchurh and Lord Khayr..
マルズバーンのうち　マヌーチュルフ殿とハイル殿は
...have already died in battle.
すでに戦死なさいました
シャプール殿は…
Lord Shapur has...
Does he mean to say even
Lord Shapur has been killed as well?
シャプール殿までも　やられたというのか
ア…アンドラゴラス王が　退却の命を伝えず　お逃げになったので…
K-King Andragoras fled without
relaying the order to retreat, so...
What?
全軍の士気が下がっ…
The morale of the entire army fell...
退却　父上は退却したのか　王都へ
Retreat?! My lord father retreated?!
To the Royal Capital?
よく戦った
You fought well.
Do you suppose my lord father is safe?
父上は　ご無事だろうか…
My uncle is a veteran and he is with him.
百戦錬磨の伯父が　付いております
I imagine he would have
left the battlefield unscathed.
ご無事で　戦場を離脱されたかと
His Majesty, the King, was concerned
for Your Highness's safety as well.
国王陛下も　殿下の身を案じておいででした
父上が　私を
My lord father was concerned for me?
早く　王都に戻らなければ
I must return quickly to the Royal Capital.
However, in order to
return to the Royal Capital,
しかし　王都へ戻るには　このまま　戦場を突っ切らねばなりません
we must cut across this battlefield.
マルズバーンたちが　これほど　倒されているということは
If this many Marzbāns have been killed,
王都までの道は　ルシタニア兵であふれ返っていると思われます
the path to the Royal Capital is likely
to be awash with Lusitanian soldiers.
そうか…
I see...
我が友　ナルサスを頼りましょう
Let us look to my friend Narsus for assistance.
What?
That's thegignal to return
to camp! Look lively now!
帰還の合図だ　もたもたするな
It's over.
終わったな
Yes.
しかし　パルスに圧勝とはな
But to win an overwhelming victory against Pars!
あの銀仮面の客将の策が　これほどとは
I never thought that
silver-masked guest general's ploys
would be this effective.
So frightful!
怖い怖い　こんな炎に焼かれて死ぬのは御免…
Give me any other death than
to be burned by these flames.
Wha?!
Glory to Pars!
パルスに栄光あれ
パルス兵は不死身か
Are Parsian soldiers invincible?!
パルス軍のなんという強さだ
What strength the Parsian army has...
"General, Kingdom of Lusitania
Baudouin"
まともに戦っておれば　到底　勝ち目などなかった
If we had fought them head on,
"General, Kingdom of Lusitania
Montferrat"
our prospects of victory
would have been nonexistent.
"General, Kingdom of Lusitania
Montferrat"
Pars Era, the year 320, October 16th.
パルス暦３２０年　１０月１６日
On this day, in the battle
upon the Fields of Atropatene,
この日　アトロパテネ平原における戦闘で
パルス王国軍は　騎兵５万３０００　歩兵７万４０００の戦死者を出し
the Kingdom of Pars lost 53 thousand cavalrymen
and 74 thousand men on foot.
And the dead of the victors,
the Lusitanian army,
勝者となった　ルシタニア軍の死者も　５万を超えた
also surpassed 50 thousand.
Go to Hell, you damn heathen!
地獄に落ちろ　異教徒め
Death to all heathens... is it?
異教徒は皆殺しにせよ…か
Thanks to a king who trusts
all to God and a son-of-a-devil,
神頼りの国王と聖職者のくせに　人殺しが好きな　罰当たりのおかげで
who enjoys killing in spite
of being a man of the cloth,
かくも多くの者が異国に屍をさらすはめになったわ
so many have ended up leaving
their corpses in foreign lands.
いいではないか　モンフェラート
What does it matter, Montferrat?
Our dead brethren get to go to Heaven
死んだ同胞は　天国へ行けるのだし
and we survivors get to
rule this bountiful land of Pars
生き残った我らは　この豊かなパルスを支配できるのだ
with its Continental Highway, its silver mines,
大陸公路と銀山と　広大な穀倉地帯をな
and its vast fields of grain.
Baudouin...
ボードワン
Do you remember the war in Maryam?
マルヤムの戦を覚えているか
When we recently conquered Maryam,
せんだって　マルヤムを滅ぼした折
子供や赤子まで　火中に投じたであろう
remember how we burned even children and babie
Oh, for they were enemies of God.
ああ　神の敵であったからな
あのときの悲鳴が　今も耳について離れぬ
I can still hear those screams
and they will not be silenced.
Though they may be heathens,
異教徒だからとて　赤子を殺すような我らに
will God bestow His blessing
upon the likes of us, who kill babes?
神は　祝福をたれたもうであろうか
Lord Baudouin! Lord Montferrat!
ボードワン様　モンフェラート様
やりました
We got him!
The King of Pars, Andragoras Ill!
パルスの国王　アンドラゴラス三世を
This Narsus...
ナルサスとは　いつぞやのお主が言っていた　ひねくれ者の友か
Is he the crotchety friend
of yours that you once spoke of?
Yes, he was once the Lord of Daylam.
はい　元ダイラムの領主でございました
聞いたことがある　父上によって　宮廷を追放されたと
I have heard of him.
He was banished from Court by my lord father.
数年前　三国同盟が我が国に侵入した折
A few years ago,
when the Alliance of
Three Kingdoms invaded our kingdom,
he is the man who sent the enemy packing
兵を一人も使わずに　敵軍を退散させた男です
without sending a single soldier into battle.
王の息子の私に　会ってくれるだろうか…
Will he meet with me, the son of the King?
そこは　それ　幸いというのも妙ですが　このありさま
That is where, it might be
strange to call it fortunate,
but given our plight...
ひねくれ者ゆえ　我々惨めな敗残者を拒みはしません
Being the crotchety man that he is,
he will not refuse such
wretchedly vanquished men as us.
惨めな敗残者…
Wretchedly vanquished men...
Nothing more can be done today.
今日のところは　もうどうしようもございません
Together with His Majesty, the King,
we will seek to retaliate at a later date,
後日　国王陛下と共に復讐戦を挑み　敵を討ちましょう
and we will avenge ourselves.
Right now,
今は　生きてこそでございます
what we must do to that end is to survive.
I am sorry, I know you must be tired.
お疲れのところ　申し訳ございません
もう少しご辛抱くださいませ　殿下
Please bear with me for a
little longer, Your Highness.
I am told that Narsus lives up this way.
ナルサスは　この先に住んでいると聞いています
山荘に引きこもって
I hear he has withdrawn to a mountain retreat,
spending his life painting and
reading books from other lands.
異国の書を読んだり　絵を描いて暮らしているそうです
Narsus likes to paint?
ナルサスは　絵が好きなのか
まあ…　誰にでも欠点はあるものでして
Well...
Everyone has their flaws.
That man knows of the
movements of celestial bodies,
あの男は　天行の運行　異国の地理　歴史の変化
the geography of foreign lands,
how history has changed over time...
There is nothing he does not know about.
なんでも知らぬことは　ございません
But there is just one thing...
ですが　たった一つ　自分の絵の技量についてだけは
With regards to his own skill as a painter,
いわゆる　下手の横好き…
he is what you might call an inept enthusiast.
Advance any farther
それ以上進むと　今度は　顔の真ん中にお見舞いするぞ
and this time, I will stick one
in the middle of your face.
Beyond this point is the
residence of Lord Narsus of Daylam.
ここからはダイラムの領主　ナルサス様のお住まいだ
Daryun...
ダリューン
ケガをしないうちに　立ち去れ
Leave before you find yourself injured.
エラムか　俺は　ダリューンだ
Is that you, Elam?!
I am Daryun!
お前のご主人に会いに来た　ここを通してもらえぬか
I have come to see your master!
Will you not let us pass?!
これは…　ダリューン様
Why, Lord Daryun!
It has been so long!
お久しぶりでございます
知らぬこととはいえ　失礼をいたしました
Though I did not know,
it was rude of me to act as I did.
背が伸びたな　エラム　お前の主人は息災か
You have grown taller, Elam.
Is your master in good health?
Yes, he is well.
はい　お元気でいらっしゃいます
And is he still at it?
で　あれか　相変わらず　うまくもない絵を描いては捨てているのか
Producing poor paintings and
then tossing them away as always?
I do not know a good painting from a bad.
絵の善しあしは　私には分かりません
私は　両親の遺言で　ナルサス様のお世話をするだけです
I merely look after Lord Narsus
as my late parents wished.
After all, it was Lord Narsus
who freed my parents from slavery.
両親を奴隷から自由にしてくださったのは　ナルサス様ですから
Narsus, it is I, Daryun!
ナルサス　俺だ　ダリューンだ
名乗る必要はない　騒々しいヤツめ
No need to announce yourself,
you raucous bastard.
I heard your voice from a whole farsang away.
お主の声は　１ファルサングも遠くから　聞こえておったぞ
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journey's beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go, drifting
When a tale that is shapeless
Spreads across the moonlight
The treasure that is within you
Melts away into the wind now
Tomorrow, try to take
wing as your unvarnished self
Sometime, somewhere,
you wanted this, remember?
You can hear it, can't you?
There; that shining dream from that day
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journey's beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go
Oh, 'til this dream comes to an end
The master of the mountain retreat
山荘の主人は　ダリューンほどではないにしても
may not have been as impressive as Daryun,
背が高く　均整の取れた体つきをしていた
but he was tall and had
a well-proportioned frame.
次回　厭世の軍師
Next time, "The World-Weary Strategist."
"Chapter VI
The World-Weary Strategist"
少年は　そして王となる
And thus, the boy would become king.